<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Machine-learning | euccas.github.io]]></title>
  <link href="http://euccas.github.io/categories/machine-learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://euccas.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-11-26T22:45:35-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://euccas.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[euccas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Get Start on Machine Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://euccas.github.io/blog/20170106/get-start-on-machine-learning.html"/>
    <updated>2017-01-06T23:17:40-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://euccas.github.io/blog/20170106/get-start-on-machine-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So here comes 2017, a year when you hear people talk about the words <em>Machine Learning</em>, <em>Reinforcement Learning</em>, and <em>Artificial Intelligence</em> everywhere.</p>

<p>Last year when Mark Zuckberg was working on building Jarvis, I didn’t spend much time on AI or Machine Learning. But I know the efforts I made last year get me ready to start on it right now.</p>

<p>Tonight I just talked to a former colleague who is working at Nvidia, and he gave me a few helpful suggestions about getting started on machine learning according to his own experience. Here are some of his advices:</p>

<!--more-->

<ul>
  <li>Set a goal: What do you want to achieve with the knowledge of Machine Learning?</li>
  <li>Learn the fundamentals: <a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/machine-learning">Andrew Ng’s course</a> on Coursera</li>
  <li>If you’d like to have more courses, take <a href="http://cs231n.stanford.edu/">Standford CS231n</a></li>
  <li>Learn to use the frameworks: <a href="https://www.tensorflow.org/">Tensor Flow</a>, <a href="http://caffe.berkeleyvision.org/">Caffe</a></li>
  <li>Work on projects with real data (very important): get from <a href="https://www.kaggle.com/">Kaggle.com</a></li>
  <li>Follow <a href="https://openai.com/">OpenAI</a> and <a href="https://deepmind.com/">DeepMind</a></li>
  <li>Master Python if you haven’t</li>
  <li>Make sure your computer has a powerful GPU :)</li>
</ul>

<p>Some people I know might think Machine Learning or AI is sort of irrelevant to what I’m working on. That’s not what I think though. Even if it is irrelevant today, it will become relevant sooner than expected. Machine Learning is not a fad. It’s the way how technology works tomorrow. If you can’t master it, at least you need have a good understanding of it.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/post_images/2017/20170107-larrypage.jpg" width="640"></p>

<p><em>Image source: Medium <a href="https://medium.com/the-mission/20-things-i-ve-learned-from-larry-page-4f83674a1a52#.elpww9snf">“20 things I’ve learned from Larry Page”</a></em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
