<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Postgresql | euccas.github.io]]></title>
  <link href="http://euccas.github.io/categories/postgresql/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://euccas.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-07T00:25:34-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://euccas.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[euccas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PostgreSQL: Understand PG Errors]]></title>
    <link href="http://euccas.github.io/20161217/postgresql-understand-pg-errors.html"/>
    <updated>2016-12-17T09:06:21-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://euccas.github.io/20161217/postgresql-understand-pg-errors</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When using Ruby Gem <code>pg</code> and establish database connections to a PostgreSQL database, you’ll see PG errors when the database connection becomes problematic. In my experience, two typical PG errors are <code>PG::AdminShutdown</code> and <code>PG::UnableToSend</code>.</p>

<h1 id="error-pgadminshutdown">Error PG::AdminShutdown</h1>

<p>The error message contains the following information:</p>

<p><code>
FATAL:  terminating connection due to administrator command (PG::AdminShutdown) server closed the connection unexpectedly
      This probably means the server terminated abnormally
      before or while processing the request.
</code></p>

<p>The PG::AdminShutdown error could be caused by database server receiving SIGTERM/SIGINT/SIGQUIT or kill command on the connection process. Each system signal shut down server processes in different manners, see the <a href="https://www.pgadmin.org/docs/1.4/pg/postmaster-shutdown.html">pgadmin document</a> to know the details.</p>

<p>When you hit the PG::AdminShutdown error, you’ll like to check if the database server gets restarted and if the server resumes to the normal state.</p>

<h1 id="error-pgunabletosend">Error PG::UnabletoSend</h1>

<p>The error message looks like:</p>

<p><code>
server closed the connection unexpectedly (PG::UnableToSend)
This probably means the server terminated abnormally before or while processing the request.
</code></p>

<p>The PG::UnabletoSend error usually means a connection timeout or network issue. It could be a temporary issue though. You can check if the other connections to the database server work well or not.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
